Midwifery Collection, 1972-1999
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Midwifery collection
1972-1999
MS 454
6 boxes (3 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
The Midwifery Collection includes articles, pamphlets, periodicals, by-laws, and newsletters pertaining to the practice of midwifery and home birth. Included are publications of the Alliance of Radical Midwives, the Alternative Birth Association, National Midwives Association and the American College of Nurse Midwives. The collection also contains information on schools and training for midwifery, insurance, legal status, and protocols of practice.
The Midwifery Collection is comprised entirely of printed materials such as articles, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, periodicals, by-laws, and newsletters pertaining to the practice of midwifery and home birth. Included are publications of organizations such as the Alliance of Radical Midwives, the Alternative Birth Association, National Midwives Association and the American College of Nurse Midwives. There are also files arranged by region, primarily in the United States. The collection also contains information on schools and training for Midwifery, insurance, legal status, and protocols of practice. The collection dates from 1972 to 1999.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
History of the Collection
Most of the materials in this subject collection were removed from the records of the Midwives' Alliance of North America when that collection was processed in 1999. Additional items were purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors.
Search Terms
American College of Nurse Midwives; Maternal health services--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Midwives--Education--History--20th century--Sources; Midwives--Legal status, laws, etc.--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Midwives--History--20th century--Sources; Childbirth at home--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Natural childbirth--History--20th century; Women's health services--United States--History--20th century--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Associated material in contained in the Midwives' Alliance of North America Records, Sophia Smith Collection.
- General Printed Material
  - Articles and clippings, 1972-93, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Pamphlets, 1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Periodicals
    - Midwife to Midwife, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Midwifery Matters, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 4a)
    - Practicing Midwife, 1979-83, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Memorabilia (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Organizations
  - Alliance of Radical Midwives, 1991, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Alternative Birth Association, 1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - American College of Nurse Midwives
    - By-laws and articles of incorporation, 1989, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Meetings and conferences, 1987-93 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Directories and membership, 1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Position statements, 1978-93, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Articles and publications
      - Miscellaneous, 1976-92, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Quickening, 1981-94 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Rural health, 1991, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Training and credentials, 1990-93, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Association for Childbirth at Home, 1975-78 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Childbirth Education Association, 1976-80 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Citizens for Midwifery, 1997-99 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Continental Friends of Midwives, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - The Farm, 1978-83 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Home Oriented Maternity Experience (HOME), 1976-78 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Homebirth, 1975-81 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - International Childbirth Education Association, 1976-93, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - National Association of Childbearing Centers, 1989-93 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - National Association of Parents and Professionals for Safe Alternatives in Childbirth (NAPSAC), 1978-89 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    [See also NAPSAC News in Sophia Smith Collection periodicals]
  - National Midwives Association, 1977-82 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous organizations, 1973-97 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Schools and training
    - New York School of Midwifery, 1990, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Seattle Midwifery School, 1984-96 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous, 1990-97 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- States and Countries
  - Alaska: Alaska Midwives Association, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Arizona, 1987-91 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Arkansas, 1984-89 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - California
    - Miscellaneous, 1976-93 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - California Association of Midwives, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Canada
    - Miscellaneous, 1983-92, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Ontario, 1985-93 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Colorado, 1983-93 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Delaware, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Florida
    - Miscellaneous, 1981-94 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Florida Friends of Midwives, 1991-92 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Georgia, 1986-87 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Illinois, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Indiana, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Kansas, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Kentucky, 1991, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Maine, 1977-91 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Maryland, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Massachusetts
    - Massachusetts Friends of Midwives, 1992, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Massachusetts Midwives Alliance, 1985-92 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Michigan, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Minnesota, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Missouri
    - Miscellaneous, 1987-93 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Missouri Midwives Association, 1991-93 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Montana, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Nebraska, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - New Hampshire, 1974-87 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    [See also Carol Leonard Papers]
  - New Jersey, 1989-94 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - New Mexico, 1984-90, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - New York
    - Miscellaneous, 1980-95 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Midwives Alliance of New York, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Midwifery Task Force of New York, 1986-92 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - New York Tocologist Association, 1983, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - North Dakota, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Oregon, 1980-83 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Pennsylvania
    - Miscellaneous, 1984-89 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Pennsylvania Midwives Association, 1989, undated (Box 5)
  - Tennessee, 1987-90, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Texas, 1986, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - General, 1986, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Cox, Kay: interview and related documents 1973-2009 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      [A/V duplication required prior to research use]
  - Utah, 1985, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Vermont, 1990, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Washington, 1984-91 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    [See also Seattle Midwifery School]
  - West Virginia, Wisconsin, and Wyoming, 1983-91 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous countries, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Subjects
  - Insurance, 1985-89, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Law and legal status, 1971-90 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Protocols of practice, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 8)